Guide to the Christopher Phillips Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- September 1959 - August 1968, New York (Plus London and Eton): School Days of a Church-Choir Groupie, Series II
  - Eighth Grade: school work and report cards; letters; Collegiate ephemera; musical and other activities; programs; Collegiate Journal and school relics; LBJ rally ticket; brochures for the new-style New York City buses; bus passes and other ephemera; photographs (photocopies). [For material relating to my bar mitzvah see "My bar mitzvah" in this series], 1963 September-1964 June (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Collegiate yearbook, The Dutchman, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - The day everything changed: leaflet from my first evensong service at St. Thomas Church, Fifth Avenue, which was also my first exposure to the St. Thomas Choir School and the start of my life as a groupie, 1963 November 3 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - St. Thomas Choir School material: includes program from the school production of The Pirates of Penzance, 1964 January-June (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - My bar mitzvah, Central Synagogue, New York, with reception at the Plaza Hotel: includes many photographs (photocopies) of me with my friends, and some family, 1964 February 1 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Programs: Metropolitan Opera; Beyond the Fringe; Poor Bitos [my first opening night, when Stephen Breimer and I saw Hermione Gingold], 1963 December-1964 November (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Camp Monomoy and Truro: letters to and from me; more ham radio material; certificates; camp ephemera; my musical activities; photographs (photocopies), 1964 June-August (Box 8, Folder 39-40)
  - Gay: Special Friendships [Les Amitiés Particulières], novel by Roger Peyrefitte: photocopy of the cover of a paperback edition. In August 1964, I was aware of and intensely interested in a new French movie made from this book about a schoolboy love affair in a boarding school and perhaps even got a copy of it in French from the New York Society Library, which I couldn't really read. I found this second-hand paperback in Amsterdam in the 1980's, and it was still powerful enough for me that I bought it to commemorate its early influence as one of the first gay books I knew of, with a school theme that made it doubly important, 1964 August (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - New York pictorial map with detailed axonometric renderings of buildings. [A 1980 version of the same map appears in Series VIII], Circa 1964 (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - A sample from the large portfolios of 19th-century magazine illustrations my father bought for us to watercolor [this one shows construction of Statue of Liberty]; very delicate, Circa 1964 (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - 1964 election: some Lyndon B. Johnson campaign material, including program and tickets for rally at Madison Square Garden, which I attended and which included singing by Joan Baez [an amazing choice considering how she came to hate him]; LBJ for the USA stickers; campaign material for Robert F. Kennedy, John V. Lindsay, Kenneth Keating, 1964 September-November (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Ninth Grade: school work; report cards; musical activities; volunteer activities; Sunday school, including report; booklet on modern Britain, extolling new towns, the Barbican and other modernist developments; two Artur Rubinstein programs from Carnegie Hall; Collegiate fund-raising brochures; relics and photographs (photocopies), 1964 September-1965 June (Box 8, Folder 45-47)
  - Collegiate yearbook, The Dutchman, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 48)
  - St. Thomas Church and Choir School: leaflets and programs, including choir school production of H.M.S Pinafore; letter from me to headmaster; other ephemera, 1964 September-1965 June (Box 9, Folder 49)
  - Frank Colapinto, fierce musical visionary and poet [1898-19??]: we befriended each other in the front pew at St. Thomas. His letters, poems and his music copying; his handwriting, in soft pencil, which is the most beautiful I have ever seen; also an iconic envelope from the G. Schirmer music shop, a redolent object for all musical New Yorkers in those decades; explanatory note by me about Frank, and copy of a 2005 letter from me trying to trace his family, 1964-68 (Box 9, Folder 50)
  - Mill Hill School, London, N.W.7 -my half-term there: preliminary correspondence about clothes and supplies, 1965 May-June (Box 9, Folder 51)
  - Days in London before school started: including start of a new obsession, buying stiff separate collars at Austin Reed Ltd.; ephemera from speech day at my cousins' school, St. Paul's [no connection to cathedral]; services at St. Paul's Cathedral and Westminster Abbey, 1965 June 10-16 (Box 9, Folder 52)
  - Mill Hill, Summer Term: school work and report card; activities; ephemera and relics; Fixtures [school schedule]; the start of my playing the organ, including specifications list for School Chapel organ and the first service I played; outings, including Wimbledon and Royal Tattoo; the little notebook I carried; the St. Thomas Choir School photograph (photocopy) and class list I carried with me in England, 1965 June 16-July 23 (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - Letters to and from me, Mill Hill School, 1965 June-July (Box 9, Folder 54)
  - Mill Hill School group photographs (photocopies) from summer 1965; correspondence from 1979 about obtaining the photographs (photocopies), 1965 June (Box 9, Folder 55)
  - The letters that began an important lifelong friendship, with Miss Rose Mary Braithwaite of London [born 1914]; some photographs (photocopies) of Rose Mary over the decades, 1965 June (Box 9, Folder 56)
  - Days in London after Mill Hill School ended, 1965 July 23-August 1 (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - St. Paul's Cathedral: programs of special services [including for JFK memorial] given to me in July 1965 by the choir verger, Arthur Morrison; in original envelope, 1963-65 (Box 9, Folder 58)
  - Sir Winston Churchill: program for his funeral and procession, given to me by Arthur Morrison, choir verger of St. Paul's Cathedral, 1965 January 30 (Box 10, Folder 59)
  - St. Paul's Cathedral: programs for special services sent to me by Arthur Morrison, choir verger [includes Albert Schweitzer and Dame Myra Hess], 1965-67 (Box 10, Folder 60)
  - St. Paul's Cathedral Choir School: Choristers' Magazine, for alumni, sent to me by Arthur Morrison, Choir Verger; six issues, 1960's (Box 10, Folder 61)
  - Summer 1965, after England: letters from Frank Colapinto, and from Stephen Breimer, who was in summer school at Tabor Academy, Marion, Mass., 1965 August (Box 10, Folder 62)
  - Tenth Grade: letters, including many from England and Mill Hill friends; material relating to the Fifth and Sixth Grade Choir I started and conducted at Collegiate; Collegiate Student Handbook; musical activities and volunteer work; school work and reports; Collegiate Journal; sermons I delivered when I conducted Monday morning chapel services at Collegiate; relics and photographs (photocopies). [Note: I cut short my year at Collegiate in April to attend Eton], 1965 September-1966 April (Box 10, Folder 63-64)
  - Collegiate yearbook, The Dutchman, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 65)
  - Michael G. Horneffer [born Geneva; died New York, 1966], my Tenth Grade French teacher at Collegiate and one of the best teachers I have ever had: photograph from Collegiate Journal [See also 1968 Collegiate yearbook tribute; and "St. John's College Choir School, Cambridge, England"], Circa 1966 (Box 10, Folder 66)
  - The pianist Constance Keene, my glamorous teacher: publicity photograph (photocopy) of her in her apartment, at 200 East 78th Street, Circa 1966 (Box 10, Folder 67)
  - St. Thomas Choir School material: includes an issue of Look magazine with the choir's photograph (photocopy); also a brochure from Salisbury School, a boarding school where many choir school alumni went, 1965-66 (Box 10, Folder 68)
  - Metropolitan Opera programs: some include photographs (photocopies) of the new opera house being built. Includes program of the first performance ever given in new house at Lincoln Center, a school performance of La Fanciulla del West, on April 11, 1966, to test acoustics; they shot off a gun from the stage first to measure the sound, 1965 December-1966 April (Box 10, Folder 69)
  - Spiral-bound music notebook in my own handwriting that I used for playing the organ at occasional Sunday school services at Central Synagogue, Lexington Avenue and 55th Street, New York, 1966 April (Box 11, Folder 70)
  - Passport #2, 1966 March 22-1971 (Box 11, Folder 71)
  - Eton College, Windsor, England: preliminary correspondence with Anthony Chenevix-Trench [Head Master] and Kenneth R. Spencer [House Master -known by his initials, KRS], includes School Rules, sent by Mr. Spencer from his holiday in Switzerland; photocopies of my later correspondence with and about Anthony Chenevix-Trench; photocopy of the book jacket from his biography; 1996 press clippings relating to allegations of beatings and the surrounding scandal, 1966 January-April (Box 11, Folder 72)
  - Eton, preliminary correspondence about obtaining Eton tails and other clothing and supplies: letters to and from Mrs. Gwynedd Wynne, the Dame [Etonian term for house mother or matron]; other preliminary forms and notes, including medical and fees, 1966 March-April (Box 11, Folder 73)
  - Eton: letters to and from me, 1966 April 27-July 20 (Box 11, Folder 74-75)
  - Eton, photographs (photocopies) of me: includes my house group photograph (photocopy); informal photographs (photocopies) taken of me; my own cardboard-mounted "leaver" portraits, by Hills & Saunders of Eton, that were given to friends as keepsakes, an Etonian custom, 1966 April 27-July 20 (Box 11, Folder 76)
  - Eton, my appointment book, Eton College Fixtures, Summer 1966: this is the copy I carried and used, 1966 April 27-July 20 (Box 11, Folder 77)
  - Eton, my activities: includes local correspondence; Eton College Organ Society; the children's choir I organized at the Eton Parish Church; local library tickets; information and regulations about the use of rowing skiffs; Henley regatta and Eton-Harrow cricket match at Lord's; notes left for me in the house; June "Long Leave" visit to the Mackinven family in Edinburgh; my visit to Mill Hill; days in London; found relics of other people. [Note: "Half" is the Etonian word for a term; my house was called KRS, the initials of my "house tutor," or housemaster, Kenneth R. Spencer], 1966 April 27-July 20 (Box 11, Folder 78-79)
  - Programs from concerts, plays and other events [includes Fiasco, Eton humor magazine published for Fourth of June celebrations, the Etonian equivalent of founder's day]: most programs are for events at Eton, but they also include events in London and Edinburgh, 1966 April-July (Box 11, Folder 80)
  - Eton, my academics: including class schedule; report cards; my handwritten History Notebook; piece of printed blotting paper issued for use in exams; list of students in my form [called Dß]; texts used, 1966 April 27-July 20 (Box 12, Folder 81)
  - Eton, my personal relics: my pocket notebook; printed notepaper and envelopes; gift booklet from Kate Blundell, my "boys' maid"; label from trousers, Tom Brown tailors; College Chapel seating plan; keepsake "leaver" photographs (photocopies) given to me; program from Organ Society Open Night concert, at which I played, along with a copy of my first, and only, review, 1966 April 27-July 20 (Box 12, Folder 82)
  - Address book, used until college, 1966 April-1971 (Box 13, Folder 83)
  - Eton: my official "leaving book," Thomas Gray's poems, stamped in gold and inscribed to me in Latin by Anthony Chenevix-Trench: Hunc Librum Christophero Marco Phillips, ab Etona Discedenti Dodo Dedit, Antonias Chenevix Trench, Magister Informator; Etonae MCMLXVI, 1966 July (Box 13, Folder 84)
  - Eton College Chronicle, school newspaper, 1966 April 27-July 20 (Box 13, Folder 85)
  - Eton College Chapel: posted service lists with music [thumbtack holes visible]; one service list, with music, from St. George's Chapel, Windsor Castle, 1966 April 27-July 20 (Box 13, Folder 86)
  - Eton, official rosters, Summer Half 1966: School List, with all students' names and addresses; The Eton Calendar, with lists of boys by form, section and specialty, including prizes and scholarships, provosts, etc., going back to 1440; Eton College Fixtures [term calendar], extra clean copy, 1966 April 27-July 20 (Box 13, Folder 87)
  - Eton College Hymn Book and Psalms and Anthems, both from Eton College Chapel: these were old copies, taken, I am sure, with permission, though I can't remember who gave that permission, 1966 April 27-July 20 (Box 13, Folder 88)
  - Eton, photographs taken during my era: illustrations from the book Eton: How It Works, and complete copy of Eton Days, a photography book by Nicholas Barlow [my contemporary at school, only six months younger] with Oliver Van Oss, Circa 1966 (Box 13, Folder 89)
  - Eton: "Quick Splashes From the Stream of My Consciousness Re Eton," informal guide written by me for my brother David F. Phillips's planned trip there in April 2001, mentioning some of my favorite haunts; one and a quarter typed pages, single-spaced, 1966 April-Jul; 2001 (Box 13, Folder 90)
  - Eton, relics of friends from later years: photograph of Hugo Vickers [by Hills & Saunders of Eton, 1969], published in November 2003 Vogue, showing him the way I remember him at school. February 1988 article from Country Homes and Interiors magazine by and about Thomas Ponsonby, with photographs of him at his home in London; phone message to me at The Telegraph Sunday Magazine, March 13, 1983, about the birth of Thomas Ponsonby's son, Sebastian, 1966- (Box 13, Folder 91)
  - Eton, list of materials from my archive requested in 2004 by Mrs. P. Hatfield, Eton College Archivist, 1966 April-Jul; 2004 (Box 13, Folder 92)
  - VC-10 aircraft: B.O.A.C. brochures, passenger "Flight Guide," information packet and other material relating to my flights to and from London, 1966 April 23, July 31 (Box 13, Folder 93)
  - After Eton, Cape Cod: includes program of benefit by Beaux-Arts Trio, 1966 August (Box 14, Folder 94)
  - A copy of the book my mother wrote during the summer of 1966 in our guest cottage ["The Little House"] in Truro: Conversational English for the Non-English-Speaking Child [Columbia University Teachers College Press, 1967, 1968], 1966 summer (Box 14, Folder 95)
  - England correspondence: includes letters from Hugo Vickers and other Eton friends with news of the school and people there [for more, see Twelfth Grade and Series III]; schemes to study at King's College, Cambridge, and exchange of letters with Anthony Chenevix-Trench, 1966 August-1967 September (Box 14, Folder 96-97)
  - Eleventh Grade, back at Collegiate: school work; report card; music and other activities, including "Pre-Debutante Dances"; reminiscence written in 2001 by Daniel Menaker, my English teacher; Collegiate Journal relics and photographs (photocopies), 1966 September-1967 June (Box 14, Folder 98-99)
  - Eleventh Grade, Modern European History class taught by C. Hugh P. Silk: my notes taken in his superb lectures; one long term paper by me about Dr. Arnold of Rugby School, who transformed the British boarding school system; class project on Britain [handwritten book], 1966 September-1967 June (Box 14, Folder 100-101)
  - Collegiate yearbook, The Dutchman, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 102)
  - Programs: Metropolitan Opera, P.D.Q. Bach, Artur Rubinstein, 1966 December-1967 April (Box 14, Folder 103)
  - St. Thomas Choir School: Gilbert & Sullivan program; program of centenary service for the school's founder, the British-born church musician T. Tertius Noble, 1967 April-May (Box 14, Folder 104)
  - Summer 1967, including trip to England, Wales, Scotland and Ireland with my parents and our family friend T. Margaret Jamer [1901-98, known as Jimmie Jamer]: relics; photograph (photocopy) of my father taken on the trip. Includes a visit to Eton; my visit to Cambridge to see David Willcocks about applying to King's College as organ scholar, including correspondence; my piano lecture-recital on July 4, at King's College Choir School, 1967 June-August (Box 15, Folder 105)
  - Photograph of King's College Choir, Cambridge, ordered from Edward Leigh photographers, Kings Parade, Cambridge [fragile], 1967 July (Box 15, Folder 106)
  - Our new car, a forest-green 1967 Volvo station wagon, picked up in England in July: brochure, 1967 July (Box 15, Folder 107)
  - Diary of our trip by T. Margaret Jamer [known as Jimmie Jamer]; includes letter to her from my father after the trip, 1967 July 3-August 5 (Box 15, Folder 108)
  - Miss T. Margaret Jamer [known as Jimmie Jamer], my parents' closest friend and traveling companion, who was a very important fixture in our family's life: photographs (photocopies) of her, along with a November 1966 letter from her to my father. [Much correspondence with her, in her distinctive handwriting, is found throughout this archive], 1960's, 1970's (Box 15, Folder 109)
  - Appointment books [3]: one has notes about the St. Thomas Choir School. I used the pocket-sized Eton College Fixtures, which I ordered from Alden & Blackwell, the Eton bookstore and stationers, each term, 1967 September-1968 August (Box 15, Folder 110)
  - College admissions: Yale Introductory Information book [80 pages] sent to applicants, 1966-67 edition; letter from Yale confirming my acceptance of their acceptance; draft for application essay for Haverford College, which was never sent, since I was accepted to Yale; relic of October 1967 trip in October to Rochester, New York, to see the University of Rochester and the Eastman School of Music, 1967-68 (Box 15, Folder 111)
  - England correspondence, with some letters from me: includes many letters from Keith Edmondson, a Mill Hill friend, about his summer visit to me in New York; Eton friends, including Hugo Vickers; also includes correspondence about choir schools and letters ordering shirts, stiff separate collars, glasses frames and other things from overseas, 1967 September-1968 June (Box 15, Folder 112-113)
  - Senior Year, Collegiate School: class work and activities; material from the Fifth and Sixth Grade Choir that I organized and conducted; a production of The Crucible with the Lenox School, in which I had a small part; dedication of new Collegiate building on 78th Street; material about the 1968 school yearbook, The Dutchman, including our tribute to our much-loved French teacher Michael G. Horneffer, who died in 1966; my Collegiate organ recital at Christmas; class lists; attendance lists; school memos; relics from Saturday detention; Collegiate Journal; other Collegiate ephemera; relics and photographs (photocopies); two letters from me to my parents written in March when they were traveling with T. Margaret Jamer [known as Jimmie Jamer], describing school and other activities, 1967 September-1968 June (Box 15, Folder 114-115)
  - Henry Adams, my Collegiate School English teacher: his written comments on one of my English essays; his report card comments; list of books to order for his class; photographs (photocopies) of Mr. Adams, at Collegiate and as a young man; 1969 Christmas card from him, with return address at 185 Lexington Avenue, 1967 September-1968 May; 1969 (Box 15, Folder 116)
  - "Philosophy of Life" school essay by me, inspired by The Forsyte Saga, concerning control versus emotion: two versions, handwritten, in French, 1967 November (Box 15, Folder 117)
  - Senior Year, non-school activities: includes program from all-black cast of Hello Dolly! with Pearl Bailey and Cab Calloway, 1967 September-1968 June (Box 15, Folder 118)
  - St. Thomas Choir School and Church: includes correspondence and my proposal for a piano lecture-recital at the school; organ notebook I kept [very hard to read, but I will interpret on request], including notes taken during two rehearsals I was allowed to attend at the choir school, 1967 September-1968 August (Box 16, Folder 119)
  - Pocket notebook, mostly full of notes on English church organists, but at the end there is an entry about Chinese art... the start of a shift, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 120)
  - British bank account, Coutts & Company, Eton branch: statements [showing, among other things, how I used to send my separate stiff collars to Britain to be cleaned]; morocco leather checkbook-wallet and statement holder from this supremely old-fashioned and fancy bank, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 121)
  - Collegiate yearbook, The Dutchman, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 122)
  - Collegiate graduation: commencement invitation, tickets and program [with organ recital prelude by me]; cards and notes; parties, with invitations and guest lists, including a breakfast I gave at home that morning and a friend's party the next night at the Playboy Club; includes photograph (photocopy) of me playing an organ recital at the start of graduation ceremony [it also shows Allen Sever, my teacher and the organist at West End Collegiate Church, one of the greatest musicians I have known]; views of the West End Collegiate Church, where graduation was held, 1968 June 5 (Box 16, Folder 123)
  - My Collegiate School diploma, 1968 June 5 (Box 16, Folder 124)
  - Collegiate alumni newsletters and fund-raising appeals, especially with photographs of people I knew [not kept systematically], 1969-2004 (Box 16, Folder 125)
  - St. John's College Choir School, Cambridge, England: correspondence about my gift of an encyclopedia and my establishment of an annual Michael G. Horneffer Scholarship of 25 guineas [£26.25 in new currency], named for my Collegiate School French teacher, who died in 1966. [More correspondence about this is found in Series III], 1968 summer (Box 16, Folder 126)
  - Summer after high school, including letters to and from my parents and T. Margaret Jamer [known as Jimmie Jamer], who were traveling in Portugal; relics of my organist job at Catholic Church of St. Philip Neri, Bronx; directions written by Wanda Toscanini Horowitz for the pianist Constance Keene when I drove Constance up to Connecticut to visit them. [That summer a Mill Hill School friend, Keith Edmondson, was visiting me in New York.], 1968 June-August (Box 16, Folder 127)
- September 1968 - June 1972, Yale (With Summers in California): Coming Out, Loosening Up, Series III
  DATE AND EVENTS:
  -- Fall 1968, I entered Yale as an undergraduate. My years were as follows: Freshman, 1968-69; Sophomore, 1969-70; Junior, 1970-71; Senior, 1971-72. I majored first in Chinese Studies, then Japanese Studies, then finally History, with a Senior thesis on Chinese history under the direction of Professor Arthur F. Wright.
  -- December 1968, when I turned 18, I was given access to my legacy of $5,000 from my aunt, Louise Phillips (1912-55). This money started me on the road to independence, allowing me to buy a car and travel.
  -- Summer 1969, I attended Stanford Summer School for introductory Chinese. It was my first experience in California, and it was a magical time. That summer I was still wearing a tie, jacket and flannel trousers to class every day; but California gave me an inkling that there was more to the world than stiff collars and the extreme formality I gravitated toward in New York and England. I taught at Donaldina Cameron House in San Francisco Chinatown in the afternoons and spent hours exploring the city. I drove across country with an Eton friend, Henry Karsten, in my brand-new 1969 Peugeot, named Lydia; on the trip back I was accompanied by my close Yale friend Paul Goldberger.
  -- June 22, 1969, saw one of the campest single moments of my life. That Sunday I entered San Francisco for the first time, and exactly as I was crossing the Golden Gate Bridge the news came over the car radio that Judy Garland had died. This, of course, started the lead-up to the Stonewall Riots the following Friday, the event that saved my life.